Pessl-Sobotka, Yella; Collection ger073
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Yella Pessl Papers1918-1979
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Pessl, Yella, 1906-1991
ger073
13 cubic ft.
This collection documents the musical career of Yella Pessl, a harpsichordist, pianist and organist.
Biographical History
Gabriella Pessl Sobotka was a harpsichordist, pianist and organist who performed under the name Yella Pessl. Born in Vienna, she had a musical career in Europe before immigrating to the United States in 1931.
Pessl was best known for her interpretations of Bach and was founder and director of the Bach Circle, a New York group specializing in lesser-known works of Bach and other Baroque composers. Pessl toured extensively in the United States, performing in as a soloist and with orchestras. She also had her own radio program and was on the faculty of Columbia University.
Pessl died at the age of 85 in 1991 in Northhampton, Mass. Her husband, Dr. Harry Sobotka, predeceased her in 1970.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains Yella Pessl's correspondence, 1930-79; musical manuscripts, arrangements, and fingered sheet music, primarily of the keyboard works of J. S. Bach, undated; scrapbooks pertaining to her concert career, 1924-56; 78 commercial and private recordings of her performances on harpsichord and piano, primarily from the 1940s and 1950s; and printed materials.
The collection also contains 194 12-inch records, 39 10-inch records by Pessl. In addition, there are 50 12-inch records and 16 10-inch records either not by Pessl or unidentifiable.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is not processed. Some boxes are described at the box level. Others are described at the item level.
Acquisition Information
The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives acquired this collection from Yella Pessl-Sobotka 1978
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Music; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Women musicians; Scores; Correspondence; Clippings; Concert programs; 78 rpm records; Scrapbooks; Pessl, Yella, 1906-1991
- Large navy scrapbook with clippings, programs. Numerous inserts, 1952-1956 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Beige scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1946-1947 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 2)
- Large black and gold scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1945 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 3)
- Large brown scrapbook with clippings, 1943-1944 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 4)
- Large brown scrapbook with black design with clippings, programs, 1942 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 5)
- Large manilla folder scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1941 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 6)
- Large black scrapbook with clippings, 1940 July 15 - 1941 February 3 (Box 1 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 7)
- Scrapbooks, loose clippings, Undated (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Large black scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1940 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 2)
- Black scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1939 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 3)
- Clippings in manilla envelope, mainly duplicates of scrapbook clippings., 1938-1939 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 4)
- Large brown scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1938 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 5)
- Black scrapbook with clippings, programs, 1936-1937 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 6)
- Scrapbook with no cover. Clippings, some programs, 1935-1938 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 7)
- Small gray/black mottled scrapbook. Programs, clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 8)
- Small brown and tan scrapbook. Clippings, programs. 1924-1935. 60p. (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 9)
- Clippings until 1930. Clippings in brown manilla envelope, 1920s (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous clippings over many years, Undated (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 11)
- Clippings concerning Yella Pessl, Susanne Bloch and Carl Dolmetsch, 1936 March 17 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous clippings in manilla folder, 1937 (Box 2 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous programs, 1930s-1970s (Box 3 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Program outlines. Columbia Broadcasting Systems, 1940-1941 (Box 3 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 2)
- Austrian programs and concert reviews, 1930s (Box 3 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 3)
- Bach Circle programs, 1937-1947 (Box 3 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 4)
- List of materials in collection, as compiled by Yella Pessl, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Curriculum vita, autobiographical materials, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 2)
- 2 small notebooks, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous notes, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 4)
- Bach Circle correspondence, materials, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence file J, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence file L, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence file M, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, concert season, 1944-1945 (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, management, 1946-1947 (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1930s-1970s (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 11)
- Fan mail and other miscellaneous correspondence, 1940s (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 12)
- Die Schule. Eine Komdie von Jella Pessl dem Vater zu seinem Geburtstag, 1918 November 23 (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 13)
- An Example of North-American Figured Bass Practices as Illustrated by the Notebook of Amy van Vleck. Also 3 reproductions from the notebook of Amy Van Vleck., Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 14)
- Articles by Pessl, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 15)
- Interview, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 16)
- Press book, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 17)
- Contracts, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 18)
- Photographs of Yella Pessl, some duplicates, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous offprints, musical subjects, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 20)
- Summer resort advertisements, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous forms, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous materials, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 23)
- Etchings, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 24)
- Student papers, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 25)
- [Hyde, Fred]. "Mersenne's Role in the History of the Tempered Tuning of Instruments", Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 26)
- [Hyde, Fred]. "Chapter I: Mersenne, The Man; His Life." Also notes, presumably by Pessl, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous catalogs, Undated (Box 4 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 28)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 5 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 6 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 7 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 8 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 9 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 10 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 11 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 12 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 13 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 14 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 15 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 16 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 17 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 18 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 19 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Music scores, Undated (Box 20 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)
- Scores, reel-to-reel tapes, microfilms, slides, Undated (Box 21 (Yella Pessl Papers), Folder 1)